A Guide to the American Rhododendron Society Papers
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #10553-q and -r
American Rhododendron Society Papers 1949-1989
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
10553-q and -r
ca. 1000 items
American Rhododendron Society
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The papers were presumed given to the Library by the American Rhododendron Society through their Executive Secretaries Barbara R. Hall of Gloucester, Virginia, and Paula Cash of Tigard, Oregon, on July 11, 1989.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of the American Rhododendron Society, containing ca. 1,000 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1 linear foot), 1949-1989, consists of general correspondence, financial papers and bound volumes, minutes of the Board of Directors, chapter information forms, "The Fundamentals of Rhododendron and Azalea Culture" by J. Harold Clarke(printed), notes and chronologies for an American Rhododendron Society history, policies of the Board of Directors, and a compilation of rhododendron varieties suitable for different areas of the United States by the Van Veen Nursery.
There are also correspondence files for several committees and topics of interest to the membership. Among these are: the Bylaws Implementation Committee, the Honors Committee, the International Rhododendron Union, the Long Range Planning Committee, the National Convention Committee, the Nominating Committee, the Committee for Planning for a National Headquarters and the Proposal to Purchase the Cecil Smith property, Plant Registrar, Pollen Bank and Seed Exchange, the Public Relations Committee, the Ratings Committee, and the Research Committee.
The general correspondence files chiefly contain correspondence with chapters and their presidents, the executive secretaries, the editor of the
Quarterly Bulletin
, and other officers of the organization.
Several issues that reoccurred frequently in this correspondence include the filling of the office of Executive Secretary (1976 Feb 28, Mar 30, Apr 1, 12, 19, & 29, May 17, and Jun 1); the publication of
Rhododendrons of China
(1979 Jun 26, & Dec 12; 1980 Feb 13, Oct 22, 23; 1981 Nov 5); the concern over the dues increase (1983 Nov 11-1984 Sep 4; and 1985 Mar 6-Apr 12); the Japanese Rhododendron Society(1984 Aug 12 & 17); the Executive Director Search Committee and the Executive Secretary (1989 Feb 11-Mar 15, n.d.); and the Endowment Fund (1984 Nov 12, 1985 Mar 30, 1988 Feb 20, and Mar 2 & 15).
The collection is arranged chronologically by topic, name of committee, or type of material.
Container List
- Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1949-1964 (Box Box 1)
- Board of Directors Meeting Minutes, 1988-1989 (Box Box 1)
- Bylaws Implementation Committee, 1980-1989 (Box Box 1)
- Chapter Information, 1978-1981 (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1975-1984 Mar; (3 folders) (Box Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1984 Apr-1989, n.d.; (3 folders) (Box Box 2)
- Financial Papers - Check Stubs, 1966-1969, 1971-1973 (Box Box 2)
- Financial Papers and Tax Records, 1963-1968 (Box Box 2)
- "The Fundamentals of Rhododendron And Azalea Culture" by J. Harold Clarke (Box Box 2)
- History of the American Rhododendron Society Notes and Chronologies (Box Box 2)
- Honors Committee, 1981-1988, n.d. (Box Box 2)
- International Rhododendron Union, 1983-1984, 1989 (Box Box 2)
- Long Range Planning Committee, 1984-1986 (Box Box 2)
- National Convention Committee, 1977-1986 (Box Box 2)
- Nominating Committee, 1981-1988 (Box Box 3)
- Committee on Planning for a National Headquarters and the Proposal to Purchase the Cecil Smith Property, 1982-1983 (Box Box 3)
- Plant Registrar, 1986 (Box Box 3)
- Policies of the Board, 1975 Apr 17 & 1981Apr 15 (Box Box 3)
- Pollen Bank and Seed Exchange, 1981-1986 (Box Box 3)
- Public Relations Committee, 1985-1988 (Box Box 3)
- Ratings Committee, 1981-1987 (Box Box 3)
- Research Committee, 1981-1987; (2 folders) (Box Box 3)
- Rhododendron Varieties Suitable for Different Areas of the United States, compiled by the Van Veen Nursery (Box Box 3)
- Cash Receipt Book Bound Volume, 1965-1970 (Box Box 3)
- Survey of Membership, 1974 (Box Box 4)
- Cash Receipt Books, 1970-1975; (two bound volumes (Box Box 4)
- Cash Disbursements Bound Volume, 1974-1976 (Box OversizeBox 4)